<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short treatise of the sacrament of penance with the maner of examination of conscience for a generall confession : wherunto is added another treatise of confession, for such spirituall or deuoute persons as frequent that sacrament / sett forth in Italian by the Reu. Fa. Vincent Bruno of the Society of Iesus.</title>
            <author>Bruno, Vincenzo, 1532-1594.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3941.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1833</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22803141</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22803141</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25753</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17069)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25753)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1788:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short treatise of the sacrament of penance with the maner of examination of conscience for a generall confession : wherunto is added another treatise of confession, for such spirituall or deuoute persons as frequent that sacrament / sett forth in Italian by the Reu. Fa. Vincent Bruno of the Society of Iesus.</title>
                  <author>Bruno, Vincenzo, 1532-1594.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 124 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Fr. Garnet's second press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and publisher suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸ B⁴ C-F¹² G⁶ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 83, 85, and 86 misnumbered 86, 58, and 83 respectively.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: slightly faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Penance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Confession --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conscience, Examination of --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25753:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25753:1"/>
            <p>A SHORT TREATISE OF THE SACRAMENT OF PENANCE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With the maner of examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Conſcience for a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Confeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherunto is added another Treatiſe of Confeſſion, for ſuch ſpirituall or deuoute perſons, as frequent that Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sett forth in Italian by the Reu. Fa.</hi> VINCENT BRV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NO <hi>of the Society of</hi> IVSVS.</p>
            <p>1597.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:25753:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25753:2"/>
            <head>THE TABLE OF THE TREATISE OF THE SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Penance.</head>
            <list>
               <item>What is the Sacrament of Penance and of the neceſſity of the ſame. Chap. 1.</item>
               <item>Of the partes of Penance. Chap. 2</item>
               <item>Of Contrition. Chap. 3.</item>
               <item>Of Confeſſion. Chap. 4.</item>
               <item>Of the conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Confeſſion. C. 5</item>
               <item>Of the matter of Confeſſion &amp; firſt of the kindes of ſinne. Chap. 6</item>
               <item>Of the number of ſinnes. Chap. 7.</item>
               <item>Of the circumſtances of ſinne. C. 8.</item>
               <item>Of ſome caſes wherin the Confeſſion is voide &amp; to be reiterated. C. 9.</item>
               <item>The maner of examining our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, concerning the firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement. Chap. 10.</item>
               <item>Of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandment. Chap. 11</item>
               <item>Of the third. Chap. 12,</item>
               <item>Of the fourth. Chap. 13</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:25753:3"/>
               <item>Of the fifth. Chap. 14.</item>
               <item>Of the ſixth and ninth. Chap. 15</item>
               <item>Of the ſeuenth and tenth. Chap. 16</item>
               <item>Of the eight. Chap. 17.</item>
               <item>Of Pride. Chap. 18.</item>
               <item>Of the third part of Penance, which is Satisfaction. Chap. 19.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>THE TABLE OF THE CHAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Treatiſe of Confeſſion.</head>
               <item>Of the profitt of often Confeſſion. Chap. 1</item>
               <item>Of the Examination of Conſcience. Chap. 2.</item>
               <item>The maner therof. Chap. 3.</item>
               <item>Towardes God: with thought. C. 4.</item>
               <item>By Wordes. Chap. 5</item>
               <item>By Deedes. Chap. 6.</item>
               <item>Towards our neighbour, by thought. Chap. 7.</item>
               <item>By wordes. Chap. 8</item>
               <item>By deedes. Chap. 9</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:25753:3"/>
               <item>Towardes our ſelues, by thought. Chap. 10.</item>
               <item>By wordes. Chap. 11</item>
               <item>By deedes. Chap. 12</item>
               <item>Of ſoro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for ſinnes. Chap. 13</item>
               <item>Of Confeſſion. Chap. 14</item>
               <item>Of the purpoſe &amp; meane of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Chap: 15</item>
            </list>
            <p>A meditation for the holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:25753:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25753:4"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF PE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAVNCE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>What is the Sacrament of Penance: and of the neceſſity of the ſame.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 1.</head>
               <p>Firſt. FOr the comfort of ſuch as are truely penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to the end that they may haue ſome knowledg of this ſo holſome a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and a briefe inſtruction, how they ought to prepare them ſelues, for the obtaining of that grace, which therin our Lord doth vſe to beſtow, togither with the remiſſion of their ſinnes: I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat firſt in generall of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, what it is, &amp; how neceſſary and conuenient for our ſaluation: And afterward what partes it hath briefly diſcourſing of euery one in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25753:5"/>particuler.</p>
               <p>Second. Penaunce therfore is a Sacramente inſtituted by Chriſt our Sauiour, in the which by the miniſtery of the Prieſt, all actuall ſinnes are remitted, and all bonds diſſolued, which concerned ſinne, wherwith mans co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience was in what maner ſoeue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> intangled: the euerlaſting puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, alſo of hell, is pardoned, and part of that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall puniſhment, which is dew to ſinne, &amp; ſometimes all the ſame wholly, according to the diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Penitent.</p>
               <p>Third. Certaine it is that if man, after he was created by God in the ſtate of Innocency, had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued him ſelfe without the ſpott of ſinn: he ſhould haue had no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Sacraments. But wheras by the tranſgreſſion of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, he, togither with all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25753:5"/>his poſterity made that miſerable ſhipwracke: he was by his moſt mercifull Creatour ſuccoured in the Euangelicall law, by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſme, as by a firſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or bourd, wherwith the wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man, hauing broken the ſhip of Innocency, might ſaue his life, and recouer the grace he loſt. But becauſe ſo many are the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and daungers of this tempeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous world, and ſo great our frailty, that often times it happeneth, that looſing by new ſinnes this firſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the grace of Baptiſme, we returne miſerablye to our owne drowning: our moſt benigne Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, vnwilling to leaue vs with out remedy, hath prouided for vs this Sacrament of PENAVNCE, as a ſecond table, wherby we may be ſaued, and deliuered from the daunger of euerlaſting death.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:25753:6"/>
               <p> Fourth. Wherby we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther how greatthe neceſſity of this Sacrament is. Wheras (according to the determination of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of TRENT) it is no leſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the ſaluation of ſuch as haue ſinned mortallye after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, than is the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, for ſuch as haue not yet ben regenerat. Wherfore, as of thoſe, which are not regenerate of water and the Holy ghoſt, it is written, that they ſhall not enter into the kingdome of Heauen: So after the loſſe of the innocency of Baptiſme If a man haue not recourſe, and be taketh not him ſelfe vnto this ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of PENAVNCE: without all doubt, vaine is the hope of his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
               <p>Fifth. This Sacrament was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a moſt conuenient remedy, and very proportionate for our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25753:6"/>inuented by that heauenlye Phiſition, who had very well felte the pulſe of our weake and feeble nature. Wherfore with his infinite wiſdome he prouided conuenient remedies, oppoſite vnto our euell diſpoſition: ordaining, that as the firſt man, after he had ſinned, did hide him ſelfe, and excuſe his ſinn before God: So if a man would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into grace: he ſhould mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt &amp; accuſe him ſelfe before men. And, as a ſinner tranſgreſſing the precepts of God, doth proudly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alte and oppoſe him ſelfe againſt God: ſo if he would obtaine par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, he ſhould humble and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate him ſelfe at the feete of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man: Alſo, that, as a man with his ſinne, doth iniury and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour vnto God: So, if he would be forgiuen by God, he ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer his ſoares &amp; diſhonour him
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25753:7"/>ſelfe before men. And finally, that looke what things he had diſordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately loued, and wherin he had taken delight: returning vnto Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, he ſhould deteſt the ſame, and conceaue againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a deadly hatred.</p>
               <p>Sixth. On the otherſide, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the rootes of PENAVNCE do ſeme at the firſt ſight to be hard and bitter: yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, for the great profitt, which a man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth therby, the fruites therof are moſt ſweet and pleaſant. For PENAVNCE doth make vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into the grace of God, and vniteth vs with him in moſt ſtraite frendſhipp. Which reconciliation in ſuch as deuoutlye receaue this Sacrament, is wont for to cauſe a ſinguler great peace and tranq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of conſcience, together with an exceeding great ſweetneſſe of ſpirite.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:25753:7"/>
               <p> Seuenth. Wherfore this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine remedye being ſo profitable vnto our ſoules: euery Chriſtian (if he loue his owne ſaluation) ought to ſhunne the being long time en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrapped in his ſinns: but ſo ſoone as he perceaueth that he hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred, any mortall filth: to runne without any delay to waſhe him ſelfe in this fountaine of the mercy of God: and this, not onely once a yeare (contenting him ſelfe only not to do againſt the precepte of the Church:) but more c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for the great and many profites which the ſoule receaueth therby, &amp; for the great daungers wherin ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth when ſhee ſuffereth her ſelfe to grow ould, with the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of ſinne ſtill lying vpon her.</p>
               <p>Eigth. Fower euells and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages there are, which mortall ſinne doth cauſe vnto the ſoule,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25753:8"/>when it is harboured therin.</p>
               <p>Ninth. Firſt: at what time ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer a man is in mortall ſinne, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afterward he falleth againe into the ſame, although it be with the very ſame circumſtances: yet, is not this ſecond ſinn of equall fault with the former: but much more greiuous: and conſequentlye, the third, greater than the ſecond: and ſo in order, infinitely encreaſeth the fault, and puniſhment of euery ſinn. And the reaſon here of is: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe how much more time God graunteth vnto the ſinner for his conuerſion and returning vnto his grace, ſo much the more encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his ingratitude: whileſt he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ill that time, and rather offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth him with new ſinnes euery day more and more.</p>
               <p>Tenth. The ſecond euell is, becauſe when a man remaineth in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25753:8"/>one ſinne, the way is made more eaſy for the fall into another. For as S. GREGORY ſaieth, Such is the burthen of ſinne, that if pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently it be not amended: with the waight thereof it draweth a man for to committ another ſinne: and this other, vnto a third: and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently there is made of many ſinnes, as it were a chaine, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny linckes, wherof one draweth the other: and who pulleth one, pulleth all. For euen ſo a man, if falling into one ſinne he doth not quickly ariſe: by litle and litle he falleth into many others.</p>
               <p>Eleuenth. The third euell is, that he which is in mortall ſinne, looſeth all the good works which he doth: becauſe they auaile not to obtaine any meritt of euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life. And although he ſhould afterward return into Gods grace:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25753:9"/>notwithſtanding, they are all loſt. Wherfore, without repentance of his ſinne, he reapeth no fruite, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes, nor of Praiers, nor of Faſtings, nor of Indulgences, no not of Martyrdome it ſelfe, and ſheding his bloode for Chriſt, if that he be not penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for his ſinn: but onely ſuch thinges are auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for the obtaining of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall benefittes, and as a diſpoſition vnto repentance.</p>
               <p>Twelfth. The laſt euell that ſinn cat ſeth vnto the ſoule: is, that al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aies the gate of Gods mercye and pardon is more ſhut againſt it. For vnto the ſinner, there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth no other good or ref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge, but onely faith, and hope of the mercy of God. But by how much the more he lingereth in ſinne, by ſo much he is farther of from mercy, and approcheth vnto gods i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25753:9"/>alwaies prouoking more his anger for to take reuenge of his ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Thirtenth. Finally: as we ſee it happeneth in exteriour thinges, that how much the more a ſpotte in a garment is ſuffered to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new, ſo much the harder it is after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to take it away: and by how much the more ſeldome a man combeth and trimmeth his haire, by ſo much the more they are knot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted together and filled with filth: So alſo a ſoule by how much the more it deferreth her purgatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with ſo much the more difficultye afterward it is clenſed &amp; purged: and ſo much the more alſo it is intangled with the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſinnes, and caſteth it ſelfe into ſo great anxietye, that with great difficulty, by neuer ſo Skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a Confeſſour, it may be freed therof: and beſides it ingendereth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25753:10"/>&amp; nouriſheth in it ſelfe the worme of conſcience which although it ſhould neuer feele in this life: yet ſhall it in the hower of death bee more fiercelye tormented therby: and much more afterward in the other worlde, where this worme ſhall neuer die, and the fier, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it ſhall be burned ſhall neuer be extinguiſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>OF THE PARTES of Penaunce.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 2.</head>
               <p>THere be three partes of the Sacrament of PENAVNCE, Contrition, Confeſſion, and Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. For as a man in three ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſinneth and offendeth God, that is, with hart, wordes &amp; deeds: So is it meere that he ſubmitt him ſelfe vnto the keies of the Church,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25753:10"/>in thoſe very thinges wherwith he offended: and that he force him ſelfe to pacifie Gods wrath: firſt, with contrition of hart: ſecondly, with confeſſion of mouth: thirdly, with ſatisfaction of workes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the firſt part of Penaunce which is Contrition.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 3.</head>
               <p n="1">1. COntrition, is a ſorowe of the ſoule, and a deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinne committed, becauſe it is an offence of God: whome we loue aboue all things: with a firme purpoſe of chaunging of life, and not offending any more hereafter.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whence we do gather that it it is not ſufficient for a man, that he may obtaine grace: only for to leaue ſinne, or to make a purpoſe of a new life: But it is neceſſarye,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25753:11"/>that he haue both the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re and the other: that is, that he be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ry and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a deteſtation of his life paſt: and withall make a firme reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing no more. And this ſorrow, it is nor neceſtary tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it be ſenſible (although this is alſo very good and profitable, when it may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) but that it be in the will: which taketh diſpleaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtaio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the ſinne commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. and reſolueth to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitt it no more.</p>
               <p n="3">3 This ſorow alſo, ought to be the greateſt of all other ſorowes: becauſe euen as God, for that he is the chiefe good, ought for to be chiefly loued, and his loue muſt be preferred before all other thinges: So alſo ſinne, by which a man of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth God, is the chiefe euell: Wherfore it ought chieflye and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all thinges to be hated: in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25753:11"/>ſuch ſorte that for nothing in all the world: no, not for to ſaue our owne life, it is lawfull any maner of way for to ſinne: whereas our Lorde ſaieth: <hi>Who loueth his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or mother more than me, is not worthy of me: and, who ſeeketh to ſaue his life, ſhall looſe it.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a man ought to wiſhe, rather to haue ſuffered what thing ſoeuer then once to haue offended God, or euer more to offend him.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Finallye: it is neceſſary that the Penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cary an hatred toward all his ſinnes committed, and be ſory for the ſame. For if he were penitent and ſorowfull for ſome onely, &amp; not for others: this were not trew Penaunce, but counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feite and feined, according to the ſaying of S. IAMES. <hi>Who-ſoeuer ſhall keepe the wholle law but offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in one, is made guilty of all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:25753:12"/> 5 Furthermore: it is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, to the end that it may be trew contrition, that a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſorowe and repent for that which is paſt: but he ought to make a firme and ſtedfaſt purpoſe of a perfect ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of life: as wee reade often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the Goſpell, that when our Lorde had teſtered health or donne any benefitt vnto any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he ſaied: <hi>Go and ſinne no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 To this Contrition alſo (if it be a true ſorow, ioined with a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of amendment) appertaineth a reſolution of making ſatisfaction vnto all ſuch as we haue in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer maner offended, whether it be in life, or in goodes, or in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: Becauſe as S. AVGVSTINE ſaieth: Sinne is not remitted, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that which was taken away be reſtored: And alſo of remitting liberallye and pardoning iniuries
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:25753:12"/>which one hath receaued of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: our Sauiour hauing ſaied: <hi>If you forgiue men their offences, your heauenly Father will forgiue you alſo your offences: but if you will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue men, neither will your Father forgiue you your offences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7 To conclude: for the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this vertew, it is neceſſary that a man haue purpoſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe all his ſinns, at the leaſt, thoſe which be mortall: &amp; to do the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce inioined him by the Prieſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the ſecond Part of Penaunce which is Confeſſion.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 4.</head>
               <p>THe ſecond part of Penaunce, is Confeſſion. For although Contrition of it ſelfe (if it be trew Contrition) hath force for to take away ſinne: yet becauſe the Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25753:13"/>cannot be trewly contrite, if withall he haue not a purpoſe of Confeſſion: and alſo becauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times it happeneth, that a man, although he be ſory, yet wanteth that perfect ſorow which of it ſelfe is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t without Confeſſion, for the obtaining of remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes, and the recouering of gods grace: therfore it is neceſſary, if he may that he go to Confeſſion in dew maner vnto the Prieſt: to the end, that by vertew of the Keies of the Church he may obtaine remiſſion of his ſinnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the Conditions of Confeſſion.</head>
               <head>Chap. 5.</head>
               <p>FOwer are the principal condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that it may be auaileable, for it muſt be entire diligent, faithfull and obedient.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Firſt it ought to be entire.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:25753:13"/>becauſe it is neceſſary to manifeſt vnto the Preiſt all the mortal ſinns which a man hath committed, and wherof he could haue reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: expreſſing euery one in particuler, in the kind and number, as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhall be declared: procuring for to tell them in ſuch maner, that the Confeſſor may vnderſtand the greuouſnes of euery one, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne whether it bee Mortall or Venial. Beſides, concerning veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſinnes, although they take not away Gods grace, but may be left vntold without ſinne: notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it is very well and profitable to confeſſe them alſo, as the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of good and ſpirituall men doth teach vs.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The ſecond condition is, that our Confeſſion be dilgent. that is, that before one goeth to Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he prepare him ſelfe with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:25753:14"/>examination of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience. which diligence euery one is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for to vſe, more or leſſe, according to the time wherof he is to make Confeſſion, and according to his owne eſtate, and profeſſion.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The third condition of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is, that it be faithfull: that is, trew and ſincere: not onely not ſparing to tell any ſinne which a man hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted; but alſo not accuſing him ſelfe of thoſe, which he hath not committed, but tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the doubtfull things as dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: and the certaine, as certaine. It muſt alſo be faithfull: that is, plaine and ſimple, not arteficially compoſed: confeſſing ſincerely all ſinnes without excuſe, or couering or diminiſhing any thing at all: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring that which is written, <hi>that our Lord geueth his grace vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the humble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:25753:14"/> 4 The fourth &amp; laſt condition is, that it be obedient: that is, that the Penitent haue purpoſe of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whatſoeuer ſhall be impoſed him by his Confeſſour: of accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the remedies for his ſinnes which ſhall be preſcribed: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding all occaſions of the ſame which he ſhall forbidd him: like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of makinge reſtitution, if he haue any thing which belongeth vnto others: or of making ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction vnto all ſuch as he oweth the ſame vnto, for whatſoeuer reſpect: And finally of accepting the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce geuen him by his Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the matter of Confeſſion: that is, of thoſe thinges which the Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent is bounde to confeſſe: and firſt, of the kindes of ſinnes.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 6.</head>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:25753:15"/>
               <p>THe Penitent ought to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe in particuler al the kinds of mortall ſinnes. and that he may knowe, which is a mortall ſinne, and which is not: He muſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that all thoſe ſinnes, which are againſt any particuler precept of God or of the Church, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly mortall. Alſo, whatſoeuer is againſt the loue and honour of God, in any matter of importance or which turneth to any greeuous harme of our neighbour: is a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſinne, and he is bound to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it: obſeruing in euery one of theſe kinds of ſinns, that he ought for to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe, not only that which he hath committed, by outwarde action, but alſo by thought, and by wordes.</p>
               <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſinns of thought in three caſes a man may ſinn mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tally, and is bound to confeſſe the ſame.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:25753:15"/>
               <p> Firſt, when, thincking of any matter of mortall ſinne, he geueth conſent with determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it in execution, if there were occaſion: although, afterward he do it not.</p>
               <p>Secondlye, when a man doth not entend to execute the ſame, but onely willinglye lingereth in that euell thought, conſenting ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly to the delight therof.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, when although he de termined it not, nor haue expreſſe will to delight therin: notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, an euell thought repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it ſelfe vnto him, &amp; he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it for ſuch, he doth not driue it away, but lingereth ſome while in the ſame, and taketh delight ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. which ſinne is properly called, <hi>delectatio moroſa,</hi> that is lingering delight: For, although there be not expreſſe conſent: yet, is there ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:25753:16"/>conſent. For, who ſeeth and knoweth that he hath fier vpon his garment, and will not quench it: it is a token that he deſireth to be burnt therby.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the number of ſinnes.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 7.</head>
               <p>BEſides the kindes of ſinnes, a man muſt alſo confeſſe the number: that is, how ofte he hath committed any particuler kind of ſinne. and when he doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member diſtinctly the number, he ought for to tell a little more or leſſe, as he can remember. if he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not do this: yet let him tell how long time he perſeuered in that ſinne: and whether he was accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to commit the ſame ſo oft as he had any occaſion, without re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſtance: and whether ſuch accaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25753:16"/>happened almoſt euery day, or ſometimes in the weeke: ſpecify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as much as he may the times that it happened vnto him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the circumſtances of ſinne.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 8.</head>
               <p n="1">1 BEſides the kindes &amp; num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of ſinnes, it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary alſo to confeſſe the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: which in generall may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced vnto fower principal heads.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The firſt is, when the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce maketh, that that ſinn which of it ſelfe were veniall, doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come mortal: as if one in ieſt ſhold take a thinge of an others, for to make him blaſpheme: or ſhoulde ſteale a penny, with a will to take much more if he could: which wil doth make, that that act which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe would haue bene veniall,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:25753:17"/>becommeth mortall.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Secondly, when the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance chaungeth the kind or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the ſinne, cauſing that act, which was firſt a ſinne of one kind to become a ſinn of another kind, or of two kindes together. As a carnall ſinne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted with a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried perſon, is adultrye: with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious or vowed, is ſacrilege: with one of the ſame kindred, is inceſt. as alſo for to ſteale in the Church, is Sacrilege.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Thirdlye, when the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance doth multiplye the ſinne, cauſing that one act is many ſinns together. as if one ſhoulde eate fleſhe vpon a Friday in Lent, or if committing one ſinne in outward action, he ſhould withall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit an other mortall ſinne with his mind and thought.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Fourthly, when the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:25753:17"/>is neceſſarily to be expreſſed, in reſpecte of ſome ſatisfaction which the Penitent is to make: as, when the ſinne may happen to be ioined with ſcandall, or notable harme or iniury of our neighbour, to whome therfore wee maye be bound either to make ſatisfaction, or recompence.</p>
               <p n="6">6 But to the end that euery one may know more in particuler thes circumſtances which he is bound for to confeſſe: he muſt obſerue and expreſſe in his confeſſion par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulerly theſe ſeuen circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces.</p>
               <p n="7">7 The firſt is, of the perſon which doth ſinne, or with whome the ſinne is committed: whether the ſame be free, or ſingle, or a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, or maried, or religiouſe, or vowed, or in holy orders, or ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in conſanguinity, or affinity.</p>
               <p n="8">8 The ſecond circumſtance is,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:25753:18"/>of the act it ſelfe, which is donne contrary vnto the law of God, or againſt our neighbour: of what qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tity the ſame is, whether great or ſmalle: whether it were much that was ſtolne, or litle: whether the perſon offended were of great importance or no.</p>
               <p n="9">9 The third circumſtance is, of the place: which in three caſes is to be confeſſed. that is, when a man hath robbed, or ſhed blood, or committed any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plete carnall act (although lawfull) in Church, or in any ſacred place.</p>
               <p n="10">10 The fourth circumſtance is, of the meanes which were vſed for the performinge of the ſinne: whether it were done with prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and entiſing others to be ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſame, or to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>curr ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, (when they were not ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of them Ieſues:) or whether
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:25753:18"/>ſacred things, or other prohibited meanes were vſed in the ſame.</p>
               <p n="11">11 The fifth, is of the end which a man pretended in ſinning, as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſtealeth weapons, to the ende that hee may kill, or killeth, that, he may ſteale, or commit adultery &amp; likewiſe when he doth or ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any thing for to induce others to ſinne, or for any other euil ende, or intention.</p>
               <p n="12">12 The ſixt circumſtance is, of the manner in which he ſinned: if ſecreatly, or publikely: with ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall of others: or with force &amp; vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: as to robbe with aſſaulting: and othr like manners which may happen.</p>
               <p n="13">13 The ſeauenth &amp; laſt circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is, of the time: as if it were forbidden vnder paine of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, that at ſuch time none ſhould commit ſuch a ſinne: In this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:25753:19"/>caſe a man were bound not onely to confeſſe the ſinne: but alſo the time of committing thereof.</p>
               <p n="14">14 Finally although for to ſinne vpon the <hi>Holy-day,</hi> is not a circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance neceſſary to bee confeſſed: yet notwithſtanding, when vpon ſome notable day, as were <hi>Good-friday,</hi> or <hi>Eaſter day,</hi> or at ſuch time as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth receiue of God, ſome ſpecial benefit, a man ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any enormous ſinne: it ſemeth more ſecure in ſuch caſe, that this circumſtance of the time (which ſo much aggrauateth the ſinne) be vttered in Confeſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>Of certaine caſes wherein the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is void, &amp; to be reiterated.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 9.</head>
               <p n="1">1 THe firſt is, want of exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: when the Penitent knowing that he hath many ſinnes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:25753:19"/>and hauing beene long time from Confeſſion, hath not firſt exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his conſcience, nor vſed any diligence to remember his ſinnes. In this caſe, if the Confeſſor doe not ſupply the default of the Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent: the Confeſſion is voide. For it muſt needes be that he leaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolde ſome ſinne or other, which he cannot remember: which were aſmuch, as if he left it of purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Secondly, when the Penitent doth tel an vntrueth in Confeſſion, in any matter of Mortall ſinne.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thirdly, when the penitent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth of purpoſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe ſome Mortal ſinne, or ſuch as he deemed Mortal: For if he did not eſteeme it mortal, but after vnderſtood that it was Mortall, it were ſufficient to Confeſſe that ſinne alone, without repeating the whole Confeſſion.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Fourthly, when the penitent
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:25753:20"/>hath not firme purpoſe and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to leaue ſome Mortal ſin, or the occaſion of that ſinne in the which he findeth himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Fifthly, when the Penitent was fallen into ſome excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: &amp; knowing it, did not firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure abſolution from the ſame.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Sixthly, when the Confeſſor is an ignorant perſon, and the Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, not ſo ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly learned, that he can perfectly confeſſe, and yet notwithſtanding hee knoweth the inſufficiency of his Confeſſor, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly he choſeth to Confeſſe to him. Becauſe in this caſe, it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that there happen many errors, which haue neede of greater cure.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Seauenthly, when the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor could not giue <hi>Abſolution:</hi> ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe he had not iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: or becauſe he was notoriouſly Excommunicate, and not tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:25753:20"/>by the Church, and the Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent knewe thereof.</p>
               <p n="8">8 In all theſe caſes aforeſaide, the Penitent is not onely bound to make his Confeſſion a-newe: but for the iniury which he hath done vnto the Sacrament, by Confeſſing euelly: he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted <hi>Sacriledg,</hi> and it is a moſt grieuous ſinne.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <head>HERE FOLLOWETH the EXAMINE vpon the Ten <hi>Commaundements: in the which</hi> are alſo comprehended al other matters wherein a man may ſinne Mortally.</head>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the firſt Commaundement: that</hi> is, of honoring God a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oue all thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 10.</head>
               <p>COncerning FAITH: if he haue beleeued whatſoeuer the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ROMAN Church beleeueth: or rather hath had ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:25753:21"/>or with wordes, and exterior ſignes, hath made any ſhew of any infidelity, or hereſie.</p>
               <p>If he haue beene ouer-curious, in deſiring to ſearch the matters of FAITH: and if he haue doubted of any article of the ſame.</p>
               <p>If he haue kept bookes, either of Heretickes, or for any other reſpect forbidden by the Church.</p>
               <p>If knowing any man to be infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with hereſie, and incorrigible by other meanes, he haue not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected him to whom he ought.</p>
               <p>If he haue learned the praiers, &amp; other neceſſary things, which eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is bound for to know: as are the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements of God, &amp; the principal miſteries of the faith.</p>
               <p>If he haue giuen credit vnto, or vſed any ſort of ſuperſtition, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntments, deuinings, either by himſelfe, or by meanes of other.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:25753:21"/>
               <p> If he haue procured by the way of lotts, for to finde out any theft, or to knowe any ſecret thing.</p>
               <p>If he haue carried about him ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious writings, for the hauing his health, or for other ende, or hath in duced others to do the like.</p>
               <p>If hee haue giuen credite vnto Dreames, or Southſayings, taking them as a rule of his actions.</p>
               <p>If for too much preſumption of the mercy of God, he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any ſin, or hath perſeuered in euil, &amp; deferred his amendment.</p>
               <p>If in aduerſities hee hath had more confidence in creatures &amp; in worldly helpes, than in God.</p>
               <p>If for too much diſtruſt of the mercy of God, he hath deſpaired of the amendment of life, or of the remiſſion of his ſinnes.</p>
               <p>If hee haue murmured againſt God, as though he were not iuſt,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:25753:22"/>or blaming his prouidence.</p>
               <p>If for feare or other humane re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, he hath had minde to offend God, or not to doe that which he was bound for his ſeruice.</p>
               <p>If hee haue curſed or blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med God, or his Saintes, &amp; other Creatures: expreſſing all the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and ſortes of thoſe blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies which he hath ſpoken.</p>
               <p>If he haue expoſed himſelfe to any daunger of Mortall ſinne, or taken delight of any ſinne which hee hath donne in time before paſt.</p>
               <p>If hee haue perſecuted, or iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with wordes, Deuout Perſons: detracting vnto their good works, and beeing cauſe that they leaue them: and in perticular, if he haue diſſuaded or hindered any from entring into Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:25753:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the ſecond Commaundement, of</hi> taking the name of God in vaine.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 11.</head>
               <p>IF hee haue ſworne that which was falſe knowing it to be a lye, or doubting of the ſame, although it were in leſt, or of a matter of ſmall importance.</p>
               <p>If hee haue ſworne to promiſe any lawfull thing, which afterward he hath not obſerued, or had not intention to performe it, at that time in which he did ſweare.</p>
               <p>If he haue beene cauſe that any did ſweare falſe, or not obſerue the lawfull oathe which he made.</p>
               <p>If he haue ſworne in manner of curſing: as men are wonte to ſay, if I doe not ſuch a thing, lett ſuch or ſuch euell happen vnto me.</p>
               <p>If he hath ſworne to do any euil or any thing which was a ſin: or not to doe any thing which was good.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:25753:23"/>
               <p> If in iudgement he hath ſworne falſe, or beeing asked by order of law, he hath not aunſwered agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blely to the intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Iudge, or hath counſailed others for to doe the like. In which caſe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ſinneth Mortally: but if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of folowed any harme of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour: he is bound to Reſtitution.</p>
               <p>If hee haue had a cuſtome of ſwearing ofte, without conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or care, to knowe whether it were true or falſe.</p>
               <p>If he haue made a vow of doing any good thing, &amp; hath not cared to performe it: or hath deferred o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermuch the execution thereof.</p>
               <p>If he haue made any vowe with a minde of not fulfilling it.</p>
               <p>If he haue made a vowe of not doing any good thing: or of doing any euell thing, or of doing any good thing for an euell ende.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:25753:23"/>
               <head>Of the third Commaundement, of Sanctifying the Holy-Dayes.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 12.</head>
               <p>IF he haue not obſerued the holy daies, but either done himſelfe, or commaunded others to do ſuch woorkes as are prohibited by the CHVRCH: or conſented vnto thoſe which doe the like.</p>
               <p>If he haue omitted to heare a whole MASSE vpon the holy-daies commaunded, without law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cauſe, or hath beene cauſe that others did leaue the ſame.</p>
               <p>If being preſent at MASSE vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any holy-day commaunded, he hath beene for any notable time voluntarily diſtracted, by talking, laughing, or buſying himſelfe in impertinent thinges.</p>
               <p>If hee haue not procured that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:25753:24"/>thoſe which bee vnder his charge doe heare MASSE vpon the holy-daies.</p>
               <p>If he haue not gone to Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at the leaſt once a YEARE, or haue not procured that others of his charge haue donne the ſame.</p>
               <p>If hee haue gone to Confeſſion, without neceſſary examination of conſcience, or without purpoſe of leauing any ſinne, or for ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe, or other humane reſpect, hath concealed any ſinne: which is a moſt grieuous Sacriledge.</p>
               <p>If euery yeare at EASTER hee hath Receiued: and that with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient diſpoſition.</p>
               <p>If with a conſcience or doubt of Mortall ſinne, he hath Receiued or Miniſtred anye Sacrament of the Church.</p>
               <p>If hee haue faſted the LENT, VIGILS, &amp; EMBER daies, beeing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:25753:24"/>bound thereunto, and if on ſuch dayes hee hath eaten prohibited meates, or hath beene cauſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doing the ſame.</p>
               <p>If for Gluttony he woulde not haue regarded to doe againſt anye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement: or if he haue ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten or druncke ouer largely, with notable detriment of his health: or if voluntarily he hath ben dronck.</p>
               <p>If he haue violated the Church with any carnall ſinne, or with ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of blood.</p>
               <p>If he haue incurred any excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication: or whileſt he was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate, haue receaued any Sacrament, or bene preſent at the holy offices of the Church: or if he hath conuerſed with excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate perſons, or ſuch as were ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of Hereſy.</p>
               <p>If he haue done any iniury or ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuerence vnto Images, Relickes,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:25753:25"/>or other ſacred thinges.</p>
               <p>If being bound to ſay his office, he haue omitted it, wholly, or any part therof: or in the ſaying of it bene voluntarily diſtracted.</p>
               <p>If for ſlouth or negligence, he hath lefte vndone any good worke vnto which he was bound.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the fourth Commaundement, of honouring Parentes.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 13.</head>
               <p>IF he haue borne litle reuerence to his FATHER &amp; MOTHER, deſpiſing them, or offending them with Deedes or iniurious Wordes.</p>
               <p>If he haue curſed his father or his mother, or detracted their good name, or diſhonoured the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their abſence.</p>
               <p>If hee haue not obeied his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, or Superiours, in iuſt matters
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:25753:25"/>&amp; ſuch as might reſult to notable detriment of the family, or of their owne ſoule.</p>
               <p>If when his Parents haue beene in neceſſity, he hath not ſuccoured them, if it were in his power.</p>
               <p>If deliberately hee haue deſired their death, that he might haue the inheritance, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If he haue not fufilled their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamentes and Laſt-Willes after their death.</p>
               <p>If he haue loued his Parentes in ſuch ſort, that for their loue, hee hath not cared to offend God.</p>
               <p>If he haue not obſerued the iuſt Lawes &amp; Decres of his ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>periours.</p>
               <p>If he haue detracted or ſpoken euill of Superiours, Eccleſiaſticall, or Seculer, of RELIGIOVS per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Prieſtes, Teachers, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If hee haue not ſuccoured the Poore, if he could, eſpecially in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:25753:26"/>or grieuous neceſſity, or if he haue beene ſterne or cruell vnto them, intreating them ſharply with wordes or deedes.</p>
               <p>If thoſe which be FATHERS &amp; MOTHERS, haue curſed, or wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed euill vnto their Children.</p>
               <p>Alſo if they haue brought them vp as they ſhoulde, teaching them their praiers &amp; Chriſtian Doctrine, and reprehending them, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting them, eſpecially in matter of ſinne, and occupying them in ſome honeſt exerciſe, to the ende they be not idle, &amp; take ſome euell courſe.</p>
               <p>That which is ſaid of Children, is vnderſtoode alſo of Seruauntes, and other of the Family, of whom care is to be had, that they knowe thinges which be neceſſary, &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the COMMAVNDEMENTS of God, and of the Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:25753:26"/>
               <head>Of the fifth Commaundement: Thou ſhalt not kill.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 14.</head>
               <p>IF hee haue carried hatred to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes any perſon, deſiring to be reuenged: and howe long hee hath ſtaied therein.</p>
               <p>If hee haue deſired any mannes death, or other great euell &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, as well in his bodye, as in good name, honor, temporall and ſpirituall goods.</p>
               <p>If he haue been angry with any perſon, with mind to doe him any harme, or to be reuenged of him.</p>
               <p>If contending with others, or in other ſort, he hath ſtriken, woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or killed: or commaunded, or conſented vnto others to doe the ſame: or (beeing donne by others) approued it, or giuen aide, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, or fauour thereunto.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:25753:27"/>
               <p> If hauing offended others, hee hath refuſed to demaunde pardon, or reconciliation: or haue not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently ſatisfied for the offence.</p>
               <p>If he haue refuſed to pardon, or to remitte iniuries to thoſe which haue offended him.</p>
               <p>If for hatred hee haue omitted for to ſpeake vnto, or to ſalute o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, although without hatred, yet with ſcandal of our Neig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bor.</p>
               <p>If in aduerſities and misfortunes he haue deſired death: or with fury and anger hath ſtroken and curſed himſelfe, or mentioned the diuell.</p>
               <p>If he haue curſed others, either aliue or dead: &amp; with what inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>If he haue ſowed diſcorde, or cauſed enmity betweene others: &amp; what harme hath enſued thereof.</p>
               <p>If for hatred or enuye, he hath beene immoderately ſorye for the good and proſperity of others as
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:25753:27"/>well Temporal as Spiritual, or hath reioiced at any harme or notable damage of others.</p>
               <p>If for anger he hath offended o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with iniurious and contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious wordes.</p>
               <p>If he haue flattered others, prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them of any ſinful thing.</p>
               <p>If with his euell example, or counſaile, or with praiſing that which was euell, or reprehending that which was good, he hath bin cauſe that any man lefte any good worke which he had begunne: or if he haue induced him to any ſinne, or to perſeuerance therein.</p>
               <p>If he haue omitted for to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and admoniſhe any perſon of any ſinne when he coulde, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bablely hoped thereby the others amendment.</p>
               <p>If he haue giuen receipt vnto out-lawes, and murderers, or with
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:25753:28"/>his counſaile and fauour, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, aſſiſted them.</p>
               <p>If hee haue ſpoken euell of his Neighbor, manifeſting any ſecreat fault of his for to diſcredit him, or cauſe him other harme.</p>
               <p>If he haue ſtroken iniuriouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ECCLESIASTICALL or RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIGIOVS perſon, wherein alſo there is <hi>Excommunication.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the ſixt &amp; ninth Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement. Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery. Thou ſhalt not deſire thy Neighbours Wife.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 15.</head>
               <p>IF hee haue had diſhoneſt &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thoughtes, &amp; voluntarily hath ſtaied and delighted therein.</p>
               <p>If with deliberate mind he haue deſired to ſinne with any Man, or
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:25753:28"/>Woman: which ſin is of the ſame kinde, of which the worke it ſelfe woulde be.</p>
               <p>If with a libidinous entent hee hath behelde Woemen, or other perſons.</p>
               <p>If he haue ſpoken laſciuious &amp; diſhoneſt wordes, with intention to ſinne, or to prouoke others vnto ſinne, and if he haue hearde wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglye and with ſenſuall delight ſuch ſpeeches.</p>
               <p>If he haue actually ſinned with any <hi>Woman:</hi> and of what quality: that is, whether a <hi>Virgin,</hi> or <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried,</hi> or of <hi>Kindred,</hi> or <hi>Affinity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If he haue with any perſon ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt nature.</p>
               <p>If he haue ſinned with perſons dedicated to GOD, either by holy <hi>Orders,</hi> or by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>owe,</hi> and if he him ſelfe had holy <hi>Orders,</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>owe</hi> of <hi>Chaſtitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:25753:29"/>
               <p> If he haue touched vncleanelye br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te beaſtes.</p>
               <p>If he haue ſinned by himſelfe, with any vncleauneſſe, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at that time he thought of any other perſon deſiring the ſame: for in that caſe there be two grieuous Mortall ſinnes.</p>
               <p>If he haue touched vnchaſtely himſelfe, or others, or permitted the ſame.</p>
               <p>If with deſire of ſinne he hath ſent meſſages, letters, or preſents, or hath beene a meane to induce others vnto ſinne, or hath giuen counſaile or aide thereunto.</p>
               <p>If he haue gonne to any place, or paſſed therby, with euil intention, for to ſee <hi>Woemen,</hi> &amp; to be deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where he muſt tel of the daungers of ſinne, to the which he hath expoſed himſelf, &amp; of the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which he hath not auoided.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:25753:29"/>
               <p> If he haue had pollution, either in ſleepe, or being a-wake, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto hee hath giuen any cauſe, or afterwardes voluntarily taken de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and complacence therein.</p>
               <p>If he haue borne carnall loue to any perſon, purſuing the ſame with deſire of ſinne, and how long time he hath perſeuered therein: and if by his occaſion ſuch perſon haue beene noted with any infamy: alſo diuers actes and ſinnes which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen between perſons which beare ſuch loue one to another.</p>
               <p>Thoſe which are <hi>Married,</hi> muſt examine themſelues in particular, if in their minde, thinking of other <hi>Woemen,</hi> or with their intention, not making their ende the beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Children, but onely carnall delighte: or with extraordinarye touchings and meanes, they haue committed any ſinne againſt the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:25753:30"/>end and honeſty of MARRIAGE.</p>
               <p>If he haue read Bokes or Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries which were laſciuious, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt with ſenſual and carnal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, or with daunger thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the ſeauenth and tenth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thou ſhalt not deſire thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours goods.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 16.</head>
               <p>IF he haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any thing which belonged vnto others, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, or violence: expreſſing the quantity of the <hi>Thefte,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, if he haue taken any ſacred thing, or out of any ſacred place.</p>
               <p>If he holde anye thing of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, without the conſent of the owner, &amp; doth not reſtore it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:25753:30"/>if he be able.</p>
               <p>If for not paiment of his debtes, (when hee is able) his creditours haue ſuſtained any damage.</p>
               <p>If finding any thing he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the ſame with mind to keepe it for himſelfe: the like of thoſe thinges which happen to come to his handes, which knowing that they belong to others, he hath not reſtored to whom he ought.</p>
               <p>If in buying or ſelling, he hath vſed anie deceipte, either in the ware, or in the price, or in the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or in the waight.</p>
               <p>If he haue bought of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which coulde not ſell: as are <hi>Slaues,</hi> or <hi>Children</hi> vnder age.</p>
               <p>If he haue bought things that he knewe, or doubted to haue beene ſtolen: or wittingly hath eaten of any ſuch thinges.</p>
               <p>If only in reſpect of ſelling vpon
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:25753:31"/>truſt, he hath ſolde for more than the iuſt price: or hath bought for leſſe than the iuſt price, in reſpecte of paiment made before hande.</p>
               <p>If he haue had a determinate will to take or to retaine, any thing of other mens, if he could: Or alſo, if he haue had a deliberate minde to gaine &amp; encreaſe his wealth (as men vſe to ſaye) by right, or by wronge.</p>
               <p>If he haue committed any ſorte of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> or made any vſurarious contracte, or entered into any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt trafficke, or partnerſhippe of merchandiſe.</p>
               <p>If hauing wages, or pay for any <hi>Worke,</hi> or <hi>Office,</hi> he hath not donne it well and faithfully.</p>
               <p>If he haue defrauded ſeruaunts, or worke-folkes of their hire: or deferred their paiment, to their hinderance.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:25753:31"/>
               <p> If he haue moued anyſute in law againſt iuſtice, or if in iuſt ſutes he hath vſed any fraude or deceipte that he might preuaile.</p>
               <p>If he haue plaied at prohibited games: or if in gaming hee haue vſed &amp; wonne by deceipt, or hath plaied with perſons which cannot alienate: as are, Children vnder age, and ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>-like.</p>
               <p>If he haue defrauded anye iuſt impoſt or tolles.</p>
               <p>If he haue committed anye Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in what ſort ſoeuer.</p>
               <p>If he haue defrauded the <hi>Church</hi> of that which was due, as are <hi>tithes</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>If by vnlawfull meanes &amp; euill information, he haue gotten anie thing which was not due vnto him, or hath vniuſtly hindered o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from the obtaining of anye benefite or commoditie.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:25753:32"/>
               <p> If he haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any help, or coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaile, or, in whatſoeuer other man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, a-betted to ſuch as haue taken other mens goods: or (being able &amp; bound thereunto) hath not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered or hindered any theft.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the eight Commaundement. Thou ſhalt not beare falſe Witneſſe.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 17.</head>
               <p>IF he haue borne any falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in iudgement, or out of iudgement, or induced others to doe the like.</p>
               <p>If he haue ſpoken any vntrueth, with notable preiudice or hurte of his Neighbour.</p>
               <p>If he haue detracted from the good name of others, impoſing falſely vpon them any ſinne, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggerating
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:25753:32"/>their defectes.</p>
               <p>If he haue murmured in weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty matters, againſt another mans life and conuerſation, eſpecially of quallified perſons, as Prelates, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, &amp; Women of good name.</p>
               <p>If he haue giuen eare willinglye vnto detractions and murmurings againſt others.</p>
               <p>If he haue diſcloſed any grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and ſecret ſin of others, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon hath enſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed infamy. Which although it were true, and not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with euill intention, yet is the ſpeaker bounde to reſtore againe the good name.</p>
               <p>If he haue vttered any ſecrete, which was committed vnto him, or which ſecretly he came to ſee, or heare, in which caſe a man is bounde to reſtore all dammages which afterward happen by ſuch reuealing.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:25753:33"/>
               <p> If he haue opened other mens letters vnlawfully, or for any euill ende.</p>
               <p>If he haue raſhelye iudged the deedes, or ſpeeches of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, taking in euil part that which might haue bin well interpreted, and condemning him in his heart of Mortall ſinne.</p>
               <p>If he haue promiſed any thing with intention to binde himſelfe, &amp; afterward without lawful cauſe hath omitted to obſerue his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which is a Mortall ſin, when the thing which is promiſed is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, or when for want of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the promiſe, our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor hath had any loſſe or damage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:25753:33"/>
               <head>Of the ſinne of Pride.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 18.</head>
               <p>IF that good which hee hath, (whether it be of Minde, or of Body, or of Fortune) hee hath not acknowledged as of God, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth for to haue it of himſelfe, by his proper induſtry, or, if hee thinke to haue it of God: yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth to haue it by reaſon of his owne merits, not giuing to GOD the glory of all.</p>
               <p>If he haue reputed vainely that he hath any vertue which he hath not, or, to be that which he is not, or, more than that which he is: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing others as inferiour vnto himſelfe.</p>
               <p>If he haue gloried in any thing which is Mortall ſinne: as, for to haue taken reuenge, or to haue
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:25753:34"/>committed any other ſinne.</p>
               <p>If to the ende that he might be eſteemed and helde for a perſon of value, hee hath vaunted of anye good, or euel, which he hath done (whether truely, or falſelye) with the iniury of God, or of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
               <p>If he haue beene ambitious, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring inordinately honours &amp; dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, &amp;c. doing to that ende that which he ought not.</p>
               <p>If to the end that he may not be noted and helde of ſmal accompt, or for feare of the ſpeeches of men he doe that which he ought not, with ſcandall of his Neighbour: or neglecte to doe that which hee ought: as, to correcte and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende others: to conuerſe with good perſons: to goe to Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; to doe other CHRISTIAN workes.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:25753:34"/>
               <p> If he haue ſtubbornly impugned the trueth: or, becauſe he woulde not ſubmitte himſelfe, or ſeeme to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uinced, if he hath obſtinately defended his manifeſt errours, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his conſcience.</p>
               <p>If through arrogancye he hath deſpiſed others, doing any thing for their diſhonour and deſpight.</p>
               <p>If for haughtineſſe and pride, he hath beene at exceſſiue charge, in Apparell, Seruauntes, Dyet, and other vanities, not conuenient vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his eſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of other Mortall-ſinnes, heare is nothing ſaide: becauſe enough hath beene ſaide already in the</hi> COMMAVNDEMENTS.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beſides al that which hath beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared aboue, thoſe which haue any ſpeciall Office, Degree, or Exerciſe, must examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:25753:35"/>of the defectes and ſinnes which in the like eſtates &amp; Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes maie particularlye hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, according vnto the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which euery one hath.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the third part of Penance, which is <hi>SATISFACTION.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 19.</head>
               <p>THE third part of PENANCE, is Satisfaction: the which is nothing elſe but a full and entire paiment of that which a man doth owe for the ſinnes he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. For two euells doth ſinne bring with it. The one is the ſpot or fault: The other, is the PAINE, or PVNISHEMENT.</p>
               <p>In Confeſſion by vertue of the Bloude of CHRIST which work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in this Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, we are clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:25753:35"/>from the ſpot or filthe, and the fault is forgiuen vs, &amp; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we are deliuered from the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting paine which was due vnto the Mortall-faulte. But becauſe it doeth not alwaies happen, that when the fault is pardoned, there is withall releaſed all the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral paine, but only the Euerlaſting: For the remedy hereof, Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſerueth: which when it is not made in this life, it muſt of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye be made in the other, in the pains of <hi>Purgatory:</hi> which (as Saint AVGVSTINE affirmeth) are ſo great, that they exceed all the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which the holy MARTYRS haue ſuffered in this life.</p>
               <p>Al the ſortes of Satisfactions are reduced vnto theſe three only. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, or other corporall aſperities: Almes and Praier, the which are correſpondent vnto three good
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:25753:36"/>thinges of a man: that is, the goods of the SOVLE, the goods of the BODY, &amp; Exterior goods. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with theſe three vertues, a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth offer vnto God a perfecte Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of himſelfe, and of all that is with in him. For by Almes he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth his External goods: with Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, he maketh a Sacrifice of his proper Fleſh: &amp; with Praier, he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth his ſpirit &amp; mind vnto God.</p>
               <p>Alſo theſe three maners of Satis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faction, are moſt conuenient for to extirpate the three principal roots of al ſins: which are concupiſcence of the Fleſh, againſt which ſerueth Faſting: concupiſcence of the Eies whereunto is oppoſite Almes: and pride of Life, for the remedy wher of we are to vſe Praier.</p>
               <p>Alſo euen as there bee three whome we offende by ſinne, that is, GOD, our Neighbour, and our
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:25753:36"/>Selues: In like manner, Praier ſeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for to pacify God: with Almes we make Satisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: with Faſting we chaſtice our Selues.</p>
               <p>And although this Satisfaction may be made two maner of waies: Firſt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſinner voluntarily of his own deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth any of theſe workes: Secondly, when the ſame woorke is enioyned him by the PRIEST in Confeſſion. By both theſe waies maye Satisfaction be made for ſinnes committed. Yet nowithſtanding farre greater and more fruite full is the Satisfaction which is made for obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the CONFESSOVR, in reſpect of the vertue of the SACRAMENT, whereof it is a part: then thoſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions which are made by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Deuotion. Beſides, that ſuch good workes as are donne volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:25753:37"/>if a man be in ſtate of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſinne: neither then, nor after, when he returneth into grace, can auaile him for to make ſatisfaction vnto God: but the workes which are enioyned by the CONFES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SOVR, although they bee of no profite when they be donne in ſin: yet notwithſtanding, afterwarde when he returneth into grace, they be of great profit: and ſerue for the due Satisfaction for ſinnes.</p>
               <p>And albeit a man alſo may Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie vnto GOD for the ſame pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhement which is due for his ſinnes, by meanes of the fauours &amp; INDVLG<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>NCES of the Church, when they be ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en as they ought, that is, in ſtate of the GRAC<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of GOD: yet not withſtanding hee ought not to neglect to helpe him ſelfe alſo with the aforeſaid works of Satisfaction, aſflicting his Body
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:25753:37"/>with Faſting, giuing Almes, and occupying himſelfe in holy Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of Praier and Meditation.</p>
               <p>Finally all manner of ſcourges &amp; chaſtiſements which Almighty GOD doth ſende vs, as Infirmity, Pouerty, Perſecutions, and other Tribulations of this life, (if a man take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with HVMIL<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>TY &amp; PA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIENCE) are of great force, not only for to Satisfy for the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral paines due for our ſins, but alſo for encreaſe of Grace and Merite. (<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:25753:38"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25753:38"/>
            <head>¶ A TREA<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>TISE OF <hi>CONFES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SION.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">FOR SVCHE SPIRITVALL PERSONS AS FREQVENT THIS SACRAMENT</head>
            <head type="sub">With a Meditation for the moſte <hi>Holy Communion.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the profit of often Confeſſion.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 1</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OWE great is the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the Sacrament of Confeſſion, &amp; howe great profite it bringeth vnto the Soules of the Faithfull, which with D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uotion do frequent it: much better is proued by that which euery one doth trie in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe:
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:25753:39"/>than either can be exerciſed by Wordes, or declared in many Volumes. Wherefore CHRIST our Redeemer knowing very well the great neceſſity which we had of ſo holeſome a medicine, woulde in the end of his Life, vnder the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of waſhing his APOSTLES Feete, leaue it vs, as it were in his laſt Teſtament, and by his example exhorte vs to vſe the ſame: &amp; this not onely for remedye of Mortall ſinnes, but alſo of Veniall. For that was the meaning of the ſame our LORD, when he ſaide, <hi>He which is waſhed, needeth not but to waſhe his Feete:</hi> That is, the condition of our fraile nature beeing ſuch that it cannot long maintain it ſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome ſpotte of Veniall ſinne at the leaſt: it is not ſufficient that a man haue by this Sacrament clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Soul from the filth of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:25753:39"/>ſinnes: but it is neceſſary to the ende that he may maintaine it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togither pure, that from time to time he waſhe alſo the Feete of his affections from the duſt of Veriall ſinnes. Nowe although the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye of ſo great a MASTER, who was the inſtitutor of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ought of it ſelfe to ſuffice to moue vs to the frequenting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: yet notwithſtanding I iudge it expedient amongeſt the many pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fites which doe reſulte thereof in our Soules, to write heere a fewe, that theſe alſo may moue vs for to imbrace more willinglye, and to helpe our ſelues of ſo ſingular a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Firſt therefore a man which doth often CONFESSE, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently doth often examine his Conſcience, is more ſecure, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the freſhe memory which
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:25753:40"/>he hath of his ſins) to CONFESSE them all: and ſo to make his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ſufficient &amp; entire: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath alſo greater ſecuritie of the remiſſion of his ſinnes, &amp; of the obtaining of the GRACE of GOD.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Thoſe which often doe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, partly becauſe they were late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Confeſſed, or ſhortly after are to return to Confeſſion: partly alſo becauſe of the continuall purpoſe which they haue, and doe often al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo renue a Chriſtian Life, and of not offending God: are more wary in keeping themſelues from euell: more eaſily they riſe againe, if they chaunce at any time to fall: and more ſtoutly they fight and reſiſte temptations.</p>
               <p n="3">3 By the frequenting of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, a man doth alwaies ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine greater light, not only for to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:25753:40"/>knowe his ſinnes, be they neuer ſo little: whereas in a faire cloath, more eaſily are ſpied ſmall ſpottes, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that which is foul &amp; ſtained: But alſo, for to knowe the rootes of them, which are his euell incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and paſſions: Wherefore when the cauſe of any infirmity is once founde out, more eaſie is the cure thereof: &amp; theſe perſons now knowing themſelues, knowe how more eaſilye to keepe themſelues from the occaſions of ſinnes, and to maintaine their SPIRITVAL health.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The ofter a man doth CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FESSE, ſo much the more through the vertue of the Sacrament, hee getteth alwaies greater grace. And by howe much more he increaſeth in grace: ſo much the more capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doth be become, and more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to receiue yet greater grace
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:25753:41"/>in other Confeſſions which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe: whence oftentimes it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth that a ſinner often going to Confe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ion, for the number of acts which he doth of penance, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth ſo much the more in this vertue, that after many Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he riſeth againe (as Saint THO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAS noteth) with greater grace &amp; feruour of charity, than he had firſt before he falled.</p>
               <p n="5">5 By CONFFSSION, there is not onely obtained remiſſion of ſinnes, but in great part alſo the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſing of the paines due vnto the ſame ſinnes: And this as well by the vertue of the Sacrament, as for that ſenſible paine of ſorrowe, &amp;, of that confuſion &amp; ſhame, which euery one hath in Confeſſing his ſinnes. And it may happen that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo oft be Confeſſed, &amp; receiue the Sacramentall Abſolution, that
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:25753:41"/>at the length (as ſaith S. THOMAS in the fourth booke of <hi>Sentences.) There may remaine no paine at all for to ſuffer in Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 To frequent this Sacrament, is a great helpe, and giueth a great light vnto thoſe which will make choiſe of an eſtate of life, wherein they maye more eaſily bee ſaued: And this, partly through the grace which ſo oft is communicated vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, whereby they are made more capeable of the diuine inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations: partly through the light which the vnderſtanding recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, by the which it may better knowe what is the will of God, &amp; their greater good: Partly alſo for the Spirtuall ſtrength which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the will, for the accepting of that which is inſpired as better: and finally for the continual coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile and direction of the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:25753:42"/>by whom in the ſteede of God they are gouerned.</p>
               <p n="7">7 He that frequenteth this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Confeſſion, is neither ſo ofte, nor ſo grieuouſly tempted of the <hi>Diuell.</hi> For euen as the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, doe not weaue their webbes, in the houſes of riche perſons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are often broken by ſuch as continually ſweepe them away: So in the Soules which are cleanſed by often Confeſſion, the <hi>Diuel</hi> cannot at his pleaſure frame or make the ſnares of his temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but rather ſeeing that his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptes are often diſcloſed vnto ſuch as can applye remedy, &amp; that he cannot eſcape without loſſe &amp; confuſion, in the ende, he runneth away: becauſe (as Saint I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ROME ſaith) <hi>Looke howe the power &amp; forc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of a Traitor, is brought to nothing, when the treaſon is reuealed: ſo thoſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:25753:42"/>Infernal Theeues doe runne awaye, when they perceiue that they are diſcouered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8 By howe much the more ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome a man is Confeſſed, ſo much the more doth he looſe remorſe of Conſcience, &amp; becommeth inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. In ſuch ſort, that thoſe ſinnes which are indeede grieuous and Mortall, doe ſeeme vnto him of no importance: Wherfore with great facility he committeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as contrariwiſe, thoſe which often are Confeſſed, do get ſo great wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe and purity of Conſcience, that they feele remorſe of neuer ſo ſmall ſinnes: which cauſeth that they abhorre all grieuous ſinnes, &amp; not ſo eaſily fall into them.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Euen as thoſe which ſeldome goe to Confeſſion, becauſe they are ordinarily in ſtate of ſinne, doe neuer finde peace, nor quiet, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:25753:43"/>they had all the conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the worlde: So on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſide, thoſe which through the often vſe of this Sacrame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, doe maintaine themſelues in grace, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they ſuffer perhaps manie troubles of this life: Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by reaſon of the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of a good Conſcience, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ioy an exceeding peace, contentment, and tranquilitye of minde.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Euen as thoſe which of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en deale with the Puiſition, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe his precepts, doe liue in good health, &amp; the longer time. So thoſe which often diſcouer the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of their Conſcience vnto their Spirituall P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſition, and of him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue remedies and cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſailes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto which they gouerne themſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es: doe more ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the health of grace, &amp; more
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:25753:43"/>ſecurelye attaine vnto euerlaſting Saluation.</p>
               <p n="11">11 The houre of Death being ſo vncertaine, by reaſon of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine and infinite chaunces, which we ſee euery day doe happen vnto men: with a more ſecure Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and with greater certainty of their Saluation, doe ſuch goe out of this life, as are woonte often to be Confeſſed, they beeing alwaies prepared for to die: than thoſe which hauing bin long time from Confeſſion, and found vnprouided by death, either haue not time to make it, or if they doe make it, yet knowe not what it auaileth them, ſuch Confeſſion being made with ſmall preparation, and often imes rather for neceſſity than for anye good deſire. Wherefore concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this pointe doth Saint AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTINE ſay: I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any man when
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:25753:44"/>he is in extremity of ſickneſſe, ſhall demaund the Sacrament of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and ſhall receiue the ſame, and ſo depart out of this world re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled: I confeſſe vnto you that we will not denye him that which he demaundeth: yet doe we not preſume that he departeth in good eſtate. He which whileſt he is in health is reconciled, and doth Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, &amp; afterward continueth for to liue wel: this man goeth ſecure out of this life: But he which at the latter ende is reconciled, and doth not Penance, whether he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from hence ſecure: I my ſelfe am nothing ſecure: yet do I not ſay that he ſhall be damned, neither alſo doe I ſay that hee ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. This I knowe not, I preſume not I pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe not.</p>
               <p n="12">12 Finally all thoſe great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites &amp; pritiledges, which (as Saint
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:25753:44"/>BERNARD writeth) Thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons doe enioy, who forſaking the world, do retire themſelues vnto a Religious life: are alſo communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated after a ſort, vnto thoſe which in the worlde frequenting the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, doe leade a Spirituall life: that is, that a man, in this eſtate alſo liueth more purelye, falleth more rarely, riſeth more ſpeedily, walketh more warely, is comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more ordinarily, repoſeth more quietly, dieth more confidently, is purged more quickly, is rewarded more aboundantly.</p>
               <p>To this ende therefore, for the comfort of thoſe deuoute Soules, which deſire to conſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es without ſpotte. I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue made this briefe treatiſe, in manner of a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Glaſſe, in the which from time to time they beholding them ſelues, maye more eaſilye deſerve
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:25753:45"/>their defectes, although neuer ſo ſmall: that they may afterward by Confeſſion take them away and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende them: where as the Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all perſons which attend vnto pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye of life, and aſpire vnto Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian perfection, ought with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to keepe themſelues, not only from Mortall ſinnes, from the which nowe by Gods Grace they are wonte to abſtain but alſo from V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niall ſinnes: And withall, to be be very carefull to bridle their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to reforme their affections, and finally to remoue as much as they maye out of their Soules all manner of imperfection.</p>
               <p>Thoſe therfore, which are wont often to be Confeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, ought eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ally in foure thinges to vſe great diligence. Firſt, in the exami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of their Conſcience. Secondly, inſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe for their ſins. Thirdly, in the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:25753:45"/>acte it ſelfe of Confeſſion. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the purpoſe and meanes of their amendment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the examining of Conſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 2.</head>
               <p>CONCERNING the firſt, that is, the examination of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: it helpeth very much for Spiritual proſit, that euery <hi>Eucning</hi> before going to reſt, a man collect himſelfe a litle, &amp; do foure things. Firſt, that he giue thankes vnto our Lord for the benefites receiued, &amp; particularly of that day. Secondly, that he Pray for grace and light to knowe his errors &amp; faultes. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, that he examine his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, running ouer all the actions of that day, whether he haue with <hi>Thought, Worde,</hi> or <hi>Decede,</hi> off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:25753:46"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:25753:46"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:25753:47"/>GOD, or his Neighbour. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, if he finde himſelfe in anye thing culpable, that hee procure with repentance, and with a firme purpoſe of amendment, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, to returne into Grace with his diuine Maieſty.</p>
               <p>Beſides this alſo, when a man is to go to Confeſſion, let him take a litle time, more or leſſe, according to the time ſince he was laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, and with greater diligence running ouer this examination fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, let him gather all his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects &amp; ſinnes which he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in all that time. Whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to will be no ſmall helpe for thoſe which haue no greatmemorye, to note euery day in the examination which they make at night, ſuch faultes as they ſhall finde: to the end, that when they are to goe to Confeſſion, they maye the better
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:25753:47"/>remember themſelues, &amp; by loke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon them ſomewhat before, make their Confeſſion with more peace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>The manner of Examination of Conſcience.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 3.</head>
               <p>FIRST, let him examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe about his laſt Confeſſion, if he omited to Confeſſe any ſinne for forgetfulneſſe, or malice.</p>
               <p>If he haue donne his Penance, and performed the counſailes and remedies preſcribed him by his Confeſſour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:25753:48"/>
               <head>Towardes God. And first by Thought.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap, 4.</head>
               <p>IF hee haue had anye doubte or curioſity in matters of FAITH, or hath giuen credite to Dreames, South-fayings, or other Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>If he haue had that memorye of God which he ought: particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the MORNING when he ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and the EVINING when he goeth to reſt: asking pardon of his ſinnes, and commending him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with ſome PRAIER to his Maieſly.</p>
               <p>If in his trot bles and neceſſities he hath had confidence in GOD, and yeelded him thankes for the benefites receiued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:25753:48"/>
               <head>By Wordes.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 5.</head>
               <p>THOSE that are bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe their Office, or other Praiers: if they haue ſaid them with due deuotion and attention.</p>
               <p>If he haue named vainlye the name of God, or complained of him, and of his prouidence, when he was in aduerſity: and if he haue ſpoken with ſmall reuerence of Saintes, and of Sacred thinges.</p>
               <p>If he haue ſworne without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence or trueth, or neceſſitye: and what intention he hath had in ſwearing.</p>
               <p>If in anye accident concerning the honor of God he haue omitted for any humane reſpecte to ſay and ſpeake that which was agreeable
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:25753:49"/>to his glorye: eſpeciallye at ſuch time as he coulde, and was bound to doe it.</p>
               <p>If hee haue made any VOVVE which he hath not obſerued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>By Deedes.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 6</head>
               <p>IF on the Holy-daies he hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with particular care vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Deuotion, and to the honour of God: and particularlye if he haue heard MASSE, and procured that ſuch as are vnder his charge, haue alſo heard the ſame.</p>
               <p>If vpon the Holy-daies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded he hath labored, or cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed others for to labour, or to doe any forbidden worke.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:25753:49"/>
               <p> If he haue kept the VIGILS, &amp; obſerued duely the FASTES of the CHVRCH.</p>
               <p>If in reſpecte of his health, or of any other thing, he hath vſed anye ſuperſtition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Towardes his Neighbour. And first by Thought.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 7</head>
               <p>IF he haue beene ready to thinke euill of others, and if in matters of importance, he haue made any raſhe iudgement.</p>
               <p>If he haue borne hatred or ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour towardes any.</p>
               <p>If hee haue deſired death, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther harme, or hath had a minde to doe any diſpleaſure to any man.</p>
               <p>If he haue enuied others, beeing ſorye for their good, or reioycing at their euell.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:25753:50"/>
               <p> If hee haue had any diſordered affection, or ſenſuall, or carnal loue towardes any perſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>By Wordes.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 8</head>
               <p>IF he haue murmured, or detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the good name of others, or falſly, or not with right intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hath ſpoken euill of others, or reuealed their ſecret ſinnes.</p>
               <p>If hee haue ſpoken euill of his Prelates and Princes, and murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt them.</p>
               <p>If hee haue giuen eare vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which did murmur, or ſpeake of vnlawfull thinges, beeing cauſe with his harkening, that they went on in ſuch ſpeeches.</p>
               <p>If hee haue omitted to vſe due correction to his Neighbour, when he was bounde &amp; able to performe the ſame.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:25753:50"/>
               <p> If he haue ſpoken vntruethes, or with preiudice of others, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggerated matters more than they were.</p>
               <p>If hee haue ſpoken iniurious wordes, or mocked, or ſcoffed, or curſed others: or wiſhed anie harme to his Neighbours, either aliue or dead.</p>
               <p>Thoſe which are Parentes, or Rulers of Families, if they haue curſed or wiſhed any cuell to their Children, or others of the Family, or if they haue not reprehended them when it was conuenient, nor procured to make them Learne whatſoeuer a Chriſtian ought to knowe.</p>
               <p>If he haue flattered others, or giuen them euill counſaile, prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them to euill, or hindering them from that which is good, or in anye other ſort cauſing them to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:25753:51"/>bee diſolute, or to committe anye ſinne.</p>
               <p>If he haue ſpoken of ſuch things as are laſciuious or vnſeemely: and if heerein hee haue giuen anye e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill edification, or ſcandall to his Neighbour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>By Deedes.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 9</head>
               <p>IF he haue beene diſobedient to his Father, or Mother, or Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, &amp; haue not caried them that reſpecte and honour which is due.</p>
               <p>Thoſe which haue a Family, if they haue behaued themſelues e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill towardes the perſons thereof: or neglected to correcte them, in
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:25753:51"/>thinges which concerne the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of GOD, and the hurte of their ſoules.</p>
               <p>If he haue ſuffered himſelfe to be ouercome with choller: and if he haue donne, or cauſed any euill to others.</p>
               <p>If he haue taken, or vſurped any thing of others, or reteined the hire of others, or broken lawfull promiſes.</p>
               <p>If in buying or ſelling he haue vſed fraude and deceit: or in other ſort damnified his Neighbour in Temporall thinges.</p>
               <p>If hee haue omitted to giue Almes, and to ſuccour the poore: according to his ability.</p>
               <p>If for anye feare, or humane re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte, he haue lefte vndonne anie worke appertaining to the glorie of GOD, his Owne, or his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Saluation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:25753:52"/>
               <head>Towardes himſelfe. And first by Thought.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 10.</head>
               <p>IF he haue eſteemed himſelfe of more worth, or goodneſſe than others, for any inward or outward goods, which he thinketh he hath: taking therein vaine-glory, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to bee for that cauſe more eſteemed than others, or commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               <p>If he haue lingered in idle, vain, or ambitious thoughts, taking ther in delight: or deſired inordinately Honours, Riches, Dignities, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Concerning Chaſtity: if he haue had temptations of the fleſhe, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny euil deſire, or vnclean thoughts, in which he hath ſtaied, or taken delight, not preſenlye reiecting them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:25753:52"/>
               <head>By Wordes.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 11.</head>
               <p>IF he haue willinglye ſpoken of himſelfe, &amp; of his own affaires, amplifying, or praiſing the ſame.</p>
               <p>Of idle ieſting, or vnſe emelye talking.</p>
               <p>If for anye impatience, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, he hath called on the <hi>diuell,</hi> or wiſhed any harme to himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>By Deedes.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 12.</head>
               <p>IF with beholding, or toucing, or by other way, he haue giuen occaſion of anye temptation: or if he haue donne any other ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſtian Modeſty.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:25753:53"/>
               <p> If he haue giuen occaſion vnto any nightly illuſion, or taken anye delight or liking therein.</p>
               <p>Thoſe which are younge, and eſpeciallye Women: if they haue vſed ſuperfluous dreſſes for vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or with intention of pleaſing others.</p>
               <p>If in eating or drinking he haue made any exceſſe: or deſired ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite things, vſing ouermuch ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitudes to ſatisfy herein rather his ſenſe than his neceſſity.</p>
               <p>Of the loſſe of TIME, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell ſpending thereof in vnlawfull Games, and other inconuenient paſtimes.</p>
               <p>If he haue conuerſed with diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute perſons, which prouoke him to euell: or if hee haue entered into anye occaſion or danger of ſinne.</p>
               <p>If he haue reade laſciuious, or
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:25753:53"/>prohibited BOOKES.</p>
               <p>Beſides all the aforeſaid things: ſuch as haue Offices, or particular degrees and exerciſes, muſt exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine themſelues of the defaultes which therein are wonte to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, aecording to the obligation of euerie one.</p>
               <p>Finallye concerning this EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AMEN, it is expedient to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhe this one thing: that when a man hath EXAMINED him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, it is not neceſſarye after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, neither ought he when he CONFESSETH, to diſcourſe through all theſe points: but it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſeth to accuſe himſelfe onely of thoſe, whereof in his Examining he found himſelfe faulty. For it is not meant by this EXAMEN, to make mens CONSCIENCES become ſcrupulous, but only to ſet down that which may ſerue for al:
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:25753:54"/>althought it is certaine that in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe pointes all perſons are not wonte to offende.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the ſorrowe for Sinnes.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 13.</head>
               <p>AFter that thou haſt examined thy ſelfe: making reflection on thoſe ſinnes which thy Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is a witneſſe of againſt thee: Firſt thou ſhalt conceiue thereof a confuſion of thy ſelfe: Conſidering thy ſmal amendment and ſpiritual profite, whereas going ſo ofte to Confeſſion, notwithſtanding thou neuer wanteſt matter to Confeſſe, but rather alwaies findeſt in thy ſelfe the very ſame defectes. For which cauſe thou haſt great cauſe to feare, that thou goeſt not with that ſorrowe and effectual purpoſe
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:25753:54"/>which were conuenient, but rather for a certaine cuſtome: Wherfore thou regarding ſo litle thy amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: it is to be feared, that God will withdrawe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee his grace, and it ſhall be ſaied vnto thee: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art lukewarme, I will beginne to vomit thee forth.</p>
               <p>Then Conſidering the greate bonde thou haſt to warde the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine goodneſſe, and howe much thy moſt louing Redeemer, hath donne and ſuffered for to drawe thee to his loue, &amp; to the obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his holy Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements: ſeeing howe thou doeſt thus ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him euill for good: thou ſhalt conceiue ſorrowe of thy ſo great malice and ingratitude: &amp; humbly asking pardon, thou ſhalt deſire him, that he will voutſafe with his Heauenly grace to reforme thy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and euil inclinations: that
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:25753:55"/>for the time to come thou maieſt no more offend him.</p>
               <p>Finally thou ſhalt make a ſirme purpoſe to amend thy life, asking of his Diuine Maieſtye Grace and helpe for that effecte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Confeſſion.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 14</head>
               <p>VVHEN thou goeſt to CONFESSION, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that whenſoeuer thou goeſt to receiue this Sacrament, thou goeſt to waſhe thy ſelfe in the Bloode of CHRIST our Sauiour, the vertue whereof worketh in the SACRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTS. See therefore with howe great reuerence &amp; thankes-giuing thou oughteſt to goe to receiue ſuch a Medicine, which ſo deerely
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:25753:55"/>coſt him who made it for thee.</p>
               <p>Then in Confeſſion it ſelfe thou ſhalt indeuour to obſerue three thinges.</p>
               <p>Firſt: to Confeſſe intirely all thy ſinnes which thou doeſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and of which thy Conſcience hath remorſe. Explicating with al the kindes of them, the number, and the neceſſarye circumſtances, as much as poſſibly thou canſt.</p>
               <p>Secondlye, to procure a plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and cleareneſſe in ſpeaking, which may proceede from an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire of beeing well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode, to the ende that thou ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be the better holpen and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by thy GHOSTLY FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER: Wheras the Scripture ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: <hi>Qui abſcondit ſcelera ſua non dirigetur.</hi> Who hideth his offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhall not be directed. Thou muſt therefore tell them ſincerelye
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:25753:56"/>not hiding, not excuſing, nor dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing any thing: without ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous wordes, or telling of ſtories, which make not to the matter: &amp; much leſſe telling the ſinnes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but accuſing thy ſelfe alone.</p>
               <p>Thirdly thou muſt goe to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, with preparation not onlie to receiue the Penance, &amp; to make ſuch Satisfaction as thy Confeſſor ſhall enioine thee: but alſo to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte all the aduiſes and remedies which for thy ſinnes, and greater Spirituall good ſhall be giuen thee by the ſame. For all in vaine doth a ſicke perſon open his infirmities to the Phiſition, if afterward he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to take the Medicines, and to obſerue the orders &amp; rules which the Phiſition hath preſcribed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:25753:56"/>
               <head>Of the purpoſe and meanes of Amendment.</head>
               <head type="sub">Chap. 15</head>
               <p>AFTER thou haſt made thy Confeſſion, thou muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to obſerue three thinges.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, preſentlye to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme the Penance enioined, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing thy purpoſe of abſtaining from thoſe ſinnes which thou haſt Confeſſed, and from all others: &amp; of auoiding the occaſions of the ſame.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is, that thou take ſuch meanes, as may helpe thee for thy amendment: hauing particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar regard of ſome defectes which thou thinkeſt are the cauſe &amp; roote of all the reſt, &amp; procuring to arme thy ſelfe againſt the ſame.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:25753:57"/> 1 The remedies which maye be vſed for to roote out anye vice, or imperfection, are either gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or particular. Amongeſt thoſe which are generall, the firſt is: a firme reſolution not to committe anye more the ſame ſinne: which purpoſe thou muſt often renue, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in the MORNING, and whenſoeuer it happneth that thou fall into the ſame.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It will helpe much, to flye the occaſions, which are wonte to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce vnto the ſame ſin: as ſportes, euill-companye, familiaritye with ſuſpeccted perſons, curioſity in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding or hearing, and ouermuch talke: for it is written, that Deathe entereth in by the Windowes.</p>
               <p n="3">3 It auaileth alſo much, diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye for to reſiſte at the verye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the temptations, dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing awaye from thee the ſparke
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:25753:57"/>of the euell thought, before it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſet fire on thy HEART. Which a man maye doe by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent recourſe vnto PRAIER, or by naming the moſt Holye name of IESVS, or by ſigning himſelfe with his Holye SIGNE, or by preſent ſetting before his eies the pittifull figure of CHRIST on the CROSSE, Wounded and peirſed for the puniſhment of our ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Verye profitable alſo for the conſeruing of the purpoſe of not offending GOD, is the often hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Worde of GOD, and reading of good BOOKES, &amp; auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to read euil &amp; vaine or laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious BOOKES: For the Worde of GOD collecteth the HEART, mitigateth PASSIONS, and filleth our WILL with good and Holy deſires.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:25753:58"/> 5 To the ſame ende helpeth alſo to goe alwaies in the preſence of god, as of a witnes of our thoughts and operations, of whom after we are to be iudged.</p>
               <p n="6">6 When any perſon feeleth anye rebellion of the fleſhe: very profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table it is to vſe the body with au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, as well in Sleeping, Eating, Drincking, and Cloathing, as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges which might be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thereunto. For whereas the fleſhe is a nouriſher and kindler of al diſordered Paſſions: howe much the more weake and feeble it ſhall be: ſo much the more feeble and fainte will the Paſſions bee alſo, which from thence ſhall proceed.</p>
               <p n="7">7 It is a very great remedye alſo for to ſhunne idleneſſe, which is the fountaine &amp; foode of all vices, alwaies procuring to haue ſome honeſt exerciſe of minde or body,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:25753:58"/>that the <hi>Diuell</hi> maye neuer finde place in the ſoule.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Much alſo helpeth heereunto, the conſideration of ſuch thinges, as may induce a man vnto feare: as of Death, of the finall Iudgement, and of the paines Euerlaſting, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for ſinners. Or the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the benefits of God, and of his Diuine promiſes, for to ſtirre vs vp vnto his loue, and to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of all that which is offenſiue to his Diuine goodneſſe.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Finally a moſt effectuall reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is to frequent the vſe of the moſt holy Sacraments of Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Communion. For (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith) the principall remedie againſt ſinne, is the grace of God, which by theſe Sacraments is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: beſides that they be inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by Chriſt our Sauiour, as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Heauenly medicines, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:25753:59"/>for to deliuer vs from ſinnes: but alſo for to heale our diſordered af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, to ſuppreſſe our paſſions, to remedy our weakeneſſe: and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, as certaine kindlers of loue, whereby our WILL beeing infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, maye more eaſilye reſiſt our euill inclinations, and ouercome all the temptations of the Worlde, the Fleſhe and the Diuell.</p>
               <p>Beſides all theſe there bee alſo other remedies more particular &amp; proper for euerye defecte, which maye be vſed and applied accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the counſaile of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour. And both theſe and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo ought to bee admitted with great courage and perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, &amp; with a ſure hope of victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, grounded on the helpe &amp; grace of Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <p>The third and laſt thing which a man ought to obſerue after Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:25753:59"/>(becauſe it is written) that it is not ſufficient to forſake euell, but it is neceſſarye alſo for to doe good:) is, for to vſe all manner of diligence for the recompence of ſinnes which we haue committed in the time paſt, with newe ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and feruour: and to procure by the memory of the euills commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to become euery daye more humble and feruent in the exerciſe of good Workes: occupying our ſelues not onelie in workes of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and of Deuotion, but more particularly in the workes of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, &amp; mercy towards our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. For as it is written, They which ſhall vſe mercy, ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo finde mercye before Almightye God.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="meditation">
            <pb facs="tcp:25753:60"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25753:60"/>
            <head>A MEDITA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION FOR THE HOLIE <hi>COMMVNION.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">THE PREPARATION FOR <hi>the Meditation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEREAS ſuch is the excellency of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the BODY and BLOOD of our LORD, that if thou hadeſt all the purity of Angels, and the holineſſe of Saint IOHN BAPTIST: thou ſhouldeſt notwithſtanding in no ſorte bee worthy to receiue it: for this cauſe in that wherein humaine frailtye doth faile (whereas our LORD wil ſo haue it, and ſo commaundeth) thou ſhalt runne vnto the helpe of his grace, asking him a great hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:25753:61"/>and burning deſire of this holy Meate, and that with a moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found humilitye &amp; reuerence thou maieſt approch to this Sacrament, to the ende that it may worke in thee thoſe effectes, which it vſeth to cauſe in the worthy receiuers.</p>
            <div type="points">
               <head>Pointes for the Meditation.</head>
               <p>THINKE with thy ſelfe that thou art mui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed of our Lord, that thou maieſt be made worthy to ſit in the company of the Angels at his Table, by thoſe moſt louing wordes: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enite, comedite Panem meum, &amp; bibite vinum quod miſcui vobis. Comedite amict, &amp; bibite, &amp; inebr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amini cariſſimi.</hi> Come, eate my Breade, and drinke the Wine, which I haue mingled for you. Eate O my frindes, and drinke, and fill your ſelues O my deereſt.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:25753:61"/> 2 Conſider how pretiouſe a meat this is, and howe dainty a banquet, to the which our LORD inuiteth thee, that thou maieſt be fed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. And verilie it is no other, but thy very LORD &amp; God, which was made man for thee: and thou a creature ſo weake, and full of all malice &amp; filth, goeſt for to receiue thy Creatour and Maker, that infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite power, and ſoueraigne beuty: thou miſerable man, goeſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that God which hauing cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated thee according to his owne Image, &amp; afterward, for the great loue he beareth thee, hauing taken vpon him thy nature and likeneſſe, deſireth to come and dwell with thee, that thou maieſt bee vnited vnto him, in ſuch ſort that thou maieſt become one ſelfe-ſame thing with him. And if that good ZACHEVS eſteemed himſelfe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:25753:62"/>happy, onely becauſe he might ſee Chriſt: what felicitye is that of a Soule, that ſhee maye when ſhee pleaſeth conuerſe with her God, ſpeake vnto him face to face, and harbour him in her very breaſt!</p>
               <p n="3">3 But on the other-ſide if Saint IOHN BAPTIST ſanctified in his Mothers wombe, and choſen of God for his fore-runner, thought not himſelfe woorthy to touche Chriſt, nor to looſe the latchet of his ſhoes: howe ſhall I vncleane ſinner preſume to touche him, and to receiue him in my houſe!</p>
               <p n="4">4 If Saint PETER prince of the Apoſtles, reputed himſelfe vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy that Chriſt ſhould remaine in his ſhippe, ſaying: <hi>Exi a me, quia homo peccator ſum Domine:</hi> Depart from me O Lord, for I am a ſinner: What ſhall I a miſerable wretche ſay, and howe ſhall I preſume to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:25753:62"/>approche vnto him, and to receiue him within my Soule!</p>
               <p n="5">5 If for to eate the Loaues of <hi>Propoſition</hi> were neceſſary ſo great puritye and cleaneneſſe (as ſayed ACHIMFLECH the high prieſt to DAVID) <hi>Si mundi ſunt pueri, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent:</hi> What ſhall I doe, a filthy ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, howe ſhal I frame to eate with my vncleane mouthe, the Breade of Angells!</p>
               <p n="6">6 If for the eating of the Paſchal Lambe which was a figure of this Diuine Sacrament, it was neceſſary for to eate it with wilde Lettice, with Vnleauened Bread, and with the Loines girded, and ſo many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obſeruations which the holie Scripture ſetteth downe: how ſhal I preſume to dra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e neere for to eate the true Lambe without ſpot, which is the Sonne of God, with out hauing ſorrowe for my ſinnes,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:25753:63"/>and without procuring to be free from the leauen &amp; malice of ſin, &amp; knowing my ſelfe to be ſo far from that purity which is required for to receiue this moſt diuine Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t!</p>
               <p n="7">7 If OZA the Prieſt only becauſe he touched the Arke of the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not with ſuch reuerence as he ought, was puniſhed by God ſo ſeuerely with ſodaine death: howe much more iuſtly ought I to feare, who not only go to touch the Arke of the teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but the moſt diuine Body of Chriſt our Lorde, the true Arke, in whom are laide vp all the treaſures of the wiſedome of God.</p>
               <p n="8">8 If the <hi>Bethſamites</hi> were alſo pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed ſo ſeuerelye by God, with the death of fifty thouſand of them onely becauſe they had beholden curiouſly &amp; without reuerence the Arke of the Teſtament: how much greater reaſon haue I of feare to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:25753:63"/>come to this Diuine Sacrament, which I muſt not only behold, but touche alſo, and receiue within my Soule!</p>
               <p n="9">9 After this, reflecting thy eies vpon thy ſelfe, ſee a little what life thou haſt lead, and conſider howe ofte thou haſt made more account of a point of honour or credit of a little chaſfe of worldly i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tereſt, &amp; of the dirte of carnal de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ights, than of the grace &amp; frindſhip of God, of the glory &amp; bliſſe euerlaſting: thou boareſt the name of a Chriſtian, but thy workes were indede rather of a <hi>Diuell:</hi> wherefore thy life hath bin rather after the maner of thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall miniſters, which making ſhewe of worſhiping Chriſt, ſaide vnto him: <hi>Aue Rex Iudeorum:</hi> And on the other-ſide ſpatt in his face, and buffeted him.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Thou therefore being ſuch a
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:25753:64"/>one, with what face wilt thou come to this Sacred Table, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to bring into thy Houſe that mirror of infinite purity &amp; cleane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to lodge the euerlaſting Worde Incarnate in that Houſe which hath beene a harbour of beaſtes, and a neeſt of ſerpents.</p>
               <p n="11">11 On the other-ſide, although thou knowe thy ſelfe thus miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and vnworthy of all good: yet muſt thou not for all this refraine, but with greater confidence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire vnto thy God: Conſidering that that Lord which with ſo great &amp; louing kindneſſe inuiteth thee, is the very ſame which traueled in this worlde, and holdeth the ſame Doctrine nowe in Heauen, which he taught here in Earth: &amp; beareth vs the ſame loue, &amp; the ſame care, and deſire which heere belowe he had for to ſaue ſinners. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:25753:64"/>ſaide when he was amongeſt vs. Thoſe that are in health haue no need of the Phiſition, but thoſe which are ſicke. And in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. I am come not to cal the iuſt, but thoſe which are ſinners. And in another place: Come vnto me all you which labour &amp; are burdened, and I will refreſhe you: So good alſo is this Lord, that he neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected any Sinner, or Weakeling, which was deſirous to come vnto him. Wherefore hee refuſed not MARY MAGDALEN, nor the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> nor the <hi>Woman</hi> which by tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching him, was cured of the fluxe of blood: yea rather, as we reade, al the blind, lame, &amp; other diſeaſed perſons ſought to go vnto chriſt, &amp; to touche him: for out of him there iſſued a vertue which healed all.</p>
               <p n="12">12 Then, O my Lord God, I am infirme, &amp; weake, I haue great
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:25753:65"/>neede for to come vnto thee my true Phiſition: if I be a ſinner I muſt go &amp; ſeek out him which may iuſti fie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me: if I be full of diſordered paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, &amp; grieuouſly loaden with the weight of my ſins: to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould I runne for eaſe, but vnto thee, who only canſt &amp; wilt helpe me! Farre greater are my ſinnes than thoſe of MARY MAGDALEN: a more vg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Leper</hi> I am, than he which came vnto thee: and in my ſoule I ſuffer another manner of fluxe, and farre more dangerous than that <hi>Woman.</hi> I am alſo blind when I ſee not thee my true light: I am lame when I walke not with paces of loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee: I am maimed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>erciſe not my ſelfe in good works, &amp; doe not helpe my Neighbours as I ought. And therefore al theſe my neceſſities and infirmities, doe force me to run vnto thee for helpe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:25753:65"/>and remedye hauing confidence in thy goodneſſe, that as thou didſt not reiecte them, ſo thou wilt not reiect me: becauſe thou ſaidſt with thy moſt holy Mouth: That thoſe which come vnto thee, thou wilt neuer caſt forth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The Praier.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ITH verye great reaſon ſweete LORD, that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Prophet, aſtoniſhed at thy great goodneſſe, and at thy exceding loue which thou beareſt towardes man ſpoke thoſe wordes: <hi>Quid est homo quia magnificas eum, aut quid apponis erga eum cor tuum:</hi> What am I O my God, of what worth or merite, that thou the moſt bleſſed &amp; moſt
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:25753:66"/>glorious God, who haſt no neede of me, nor of anye thing of mine, ſhouldeſt haue me in ſuch eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; procure in all manner poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to exalt me and magnifie me, &amp; communicate thy ſelfe, &amp; what ſoeuer is thine ſo liberallye vnto me! What am I but a little duſt and aſhes! And if I will compare my ſelfe vnto the height of thy God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, I ſhal vtterly fail in my ſight, &amp; knowe my ſelfe altogither to be nothing. And yet notwithſtanding behold thou inclineſt the heauens, and voutfafeſt to come vnto me, to repaire the ruines of my Soule, and to waſhe awaye, not with the water of the Red-Sea, but with thy owne Blood, my filthineſſe: &amp; to ſatisfy my deadly hunger, not with the <hi>Manna</hi> of the deſert, but with thy owne ſuperſubſtantiall &amp; moſt Diuine fleſhe. If that good <hi>Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion,</hi>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:25753:66"/>whoſe faith thou preferredſt before all <hi>Iſraell,</hi> vnderſtanding that thou wert comming vnto him thought not himſelfe worthy that thou ſhouldeſt come neere vnto his houſe: and thy holy <hi>Forerunner</hi> which was ſanctified before hee was borne, &amp; then whom amongſt all men there was not a greater, when hee ſawe thee come vnto him, did proſtrate himſelfe with ſo great humility at thy feete, ſaying: <hi>Tu venis ad me!</hi> How much more I miſerable wretche, all borne in ſinne, and of ſo many ſeuerall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitudes and offences towardes thee, as haue beene thy benefites towardes me, which I haue repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſo vnworthy exchange: I which for my wickedneſſe am not worthy to lifte vp my eies vnto Heauen, nor that the earth ſhould vpholde me: and if thou wouldeſt
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:25753:67"/>enter into iudgement with me, all the paines of this, and of the other life, were not ſufficient for to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe the thouſand part of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merites, thou comming with ſo great loue and gentleneſſe vnto me: ought to proſtrate my ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the earth: yea, if it were poſſible to lay my ſelfe vnder the earth, &amp; with farre greater reaſon and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, crye out, <hi>Domine tu venis ad me!</hi> O LORD doſt thou come to mee! I am not worthy that thou enter into my Houſe, but ſpeake but one only Worde, &amp; my Soule ſhall be ſafe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25753:67"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
